# Jean Pierre Bolaños

Email: j.p.bolanos@student.rug.nl Websites: GitHub, ORCID, RENACyT, LinkedIn

#### Research Profile

I am a graduate student in the Research Master in Economics and Business at the University of Groningen. I have worked on studies on export promotion programmes, firm capabilities, and export performance in Peru. I am interested in studying how multiple goals and organisational success hamper learning and adaptation. I am also interested in theoretical/computational organisational models.

#### Education

Sep 2021—to date
Oct 2022—to date
ay 2020— May 2021
Mar 2012–Dec 2016

## Research experience

Research Assistant	Apr 2017–Aug 2019
To Prof. Oscar Malca, Associate Dean International Business, Universidad del Pacífico	
Research Assistant	Jan 2016–Dec 2016
To Prof. Angie Higuchi, Universidad del Pacífico Research Centre	
Research Assistant Intern	Apr 2015–Oct 2015
To Gabriela Guerrero and Juan León Jara-Almonte, Group for the Analysis of Development	
Research Assistant	Jul 2014–Dec 2014
To Prof. Angie Higuchi, Universidad del Pacífico Research Centre	

#### Grants and awards

Agent-based modelling course scholarship (USD 50) Santa Fe Institute's Complexity Explorer	2022
Second year tuition fee scholarship (EUR 16201)	2022
SOM Graduate School, University of Groningen	
First year tuition fee scholarship (EUR 13732)	2021
SOM Graduate School, University of Groningen	
Conference travel grants (USD 4800)	2016-2018
Universidad del Pacífico Research Centre	
Honour Roll, 1st place – Research category	2016
Universidad del Pacífico	
Prize for academic performance, 1st place	2016
Universidad del Pacífico	
Valedictorian, Class of 2016–II	2016
Universidad del Pacífico	

## Peer-reviewed publications

- Malca, O., Bolaños, J.P., Rubio, J.L., & Acedo, F.J. (2021). Export market orientation and export performance in emerging markets: Insights from the Peruvian agri-export sector. Journal of Agribusiness in Developing and Emerging Economies, Advance online publication. https://doi.org/10.1108/JA DEE-12-2020-0308
- Malca, O., Bolaños, J.P., Acedo, F.J., Rubio, J.L., & Peña-Vinces, J. (2021). Relational flexibility norms and relationship-building capabilities as a mediating mechanism in export performance: insights from exporting SMEs in an emerging economy, Peru. International Journal of Emerging Markets, 16(8), 1745– 1768. https://doi.org/10.1108/IJOEM-09-2019-0735
- Malca, O., & Bolaños, J.P. (2019). El efecto de la proactividad exportadora y la orientación a los mercados de exportación en el desempeño exportador: Estudio exploratorio del sector confecciones. In S. Götz (Ed.), América Latina y Asia Pacífico: Relaciones y proyecciones de cara a un mundo turbulento (pp. 153—180). Santiago de Chile: Ediciones Universidad Alberto Hurtado. https://ediciones.uahurt ado.cl/producto/america-latina-y-asia-pacifico/

#### Conference presentations

I have presented three conference articles at the conference series "Catedra Alianza Asia Pacífico" in Lima (2016), Santiago de Chile (2017), and Mexico City (2018). In 2016 I also presented one article at the XXV International Scientific Conference Agrarian Perspectives in Prague (Proceedings).

## Teaching experience

Teaching assistant Nov 2022–Jan 2023

Financial Accourting for E&BE/International Business. University of Groningen

**Invited lecturer** Sep 2017–Jul 2019

Four undergraduate courses on multivariate statistics, international management, and international marketing. Universidad del Pacífico

**Invited lecturer** Mar 2018–Sep 2018

MBA programme (International Business module). Pacífico Business School

#### Consultancies

I have developed consultancies for multilateral organisations, government institutions, NGOs, and private companies. These include the Technical Group of Promotion Agencies of the Pacific Alliance and the Peruvian Ministry of Foreign Trade and Tourism (MINCETUR).

## Skills and languages

STATA, R, SPSS, AMOS, G\*Power, Vensim, NetLogo, MS Office, VBA, LATEX English (IELTS 8.0), French (DELF C1), Spanish (Native)

#### References

dr. Dennis Veltrop

Associate professor of Corporate Governance Department of Accounting University of Groningen d.veltrop@rug.nl

Telf. +31 50 36 37068

#### Prof. Oscar Malca G.

Associate dean of International Business Department of Marketing and International Business Universidad del Pacífico

malca oe@up.edu.pe

Telf. +51 1 2190100 #2231